<metadata>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
<pubdate>20030901</pubdate>
<title>National Land Cover Database Hawaiian Zone Land Cover Layer</title>
<edition>1.0</edition>
<geoform>remote-sensing image</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>None</sername>
<issue>None</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Sioux Falls, SD</pubplace>
<publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>References: Homer, C., C. Huang, L. Yang, B. Wylie and M. Coan, 2004. Development of a 2001 national land cover database for the United States. Photogrammetric Engineering and Remote Sensing Vol.70,No.7,pp 829-840 or online at www.mrlc.gov/publications. The USGS acknowledges the support of NOAA in development of data in this zone.</othercit>
<onlink>http://www.mrlc.gov</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>The National Land Cover Database 2001 land cover layer for The Hawaiian mapping zone was produced through a cooperative project conducted by the Multi-Resolution Land Characteristics (MRLC) Consortium. The MRLC Consortium is a partnership of federal agencies (www.mrlc.gov), consisting of the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA), the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA), the U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA), the U.S. Forest Service (USFS), the National Park Service (NPS), the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (FWS), the Bureau of Land Management (BLM) and the USDA Natural Resources Conservation Service (NRCS). One of the primary goals of the project is to generate a current, consistent, seamless, and accurate National Land cover Database (NLCD) circa 2001 for the United States at medium spatial resolution. This landcover map and all documents pertaining to it are considered "provisional" until a formal accuracy assessment can be conducted. For a detailed definition and discussion on MRLC and the NLCD 2001 products, refer to Homer et al. (2004) and http://www.mrlc.gov/mrlc2k.asp. The NLCD 2001 is created by partitioning the U.S. into mapping zones. A total of 66 mapping zones were delineated within the conterminous U.S. based on ecoregion and geographical characteristics, edge matching features and the size requirement of Landsat mosaics. The Hawaiian Mapping zone encompasses the state of Hawaii. Questions about the NLCD Hawaiian mapping zone can be directed to the NLCD 2001 land cover mapping team at the USGS/EROS, Sioux Falls, SD (605) 594-6151 or mrlc@usgs.gov.</abstract>
<purpose>The goal of this project is to provide the Nation with complete, current and consistent public domain information on its land use and land cover.</purpose>
<supplinf>Corner Coordinates (center of pixel, projection meters) Upper Left Corner: -345930 meters(X), 2132400 meters(Y) Lower Right Corner: 237210 meters(X), 1753890 meters(Y)</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<rngdates>
<begdate>19990802</begdate>
<enddate>20030222</enddate>
</rngdates>
</timeinfo>
<current>ground condition</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>In work</progress>
<update>As needed</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<bounding>
<westbc> -160.27111</westbc>
<eastbc> 154.73944</eastbc>
<northbc> 22.29111</northbc>
<southbc> -18.85833</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>None</themekt>
<themekey>Land Cover</themekey>
<themekey>GIS</themekey>
<themekey>U.S. Geological Survey</themekey>
<themekey>USGS</themekey>
<themekey>digital spatial data</themekey>
</theme>
<theme>
<themekt>ISO 19115 Category</themekt>
<themekey>imagery</themekey>
<themekey>Base Maps</themekey>
<themekey>Earth Cover</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>U.S. Department of Commerce, 1995, Countries, dependencies, areas of special sovereignty, and their principal administrative divisions, Federal Information Processing Standard 10-4,): Washington, D.C., National Institute of Standards and Technology</placekt>
<placekey>United States</placekey>
<placekey>U.S.</placekey>
<placekey>US</placekey>
</place>
<place>
<placekt>None</placekt>
<placekey>Hawaiian mapping Zone</placekey>
</place>
<place>
<placekt>U.S. Department of Commerce, 1987, Codes for the identification of the States, the District of Columbia and the outlying areas of the United States, and associated areas (Federal Information Processing Standard 5-2): Washington, D.C., National Institute of Standards and Technology</placekt>
<placekey>HI</placekey>
<placekey>Hawaii</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<accconst>None</accconst>
<useconst>None</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Customer Services Representative</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>USGS/EROS</address>
<address>47914 252nd Street</address>
<city>Sioux Falls</city>
<state>SD</state>
<postal>57198-0001</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>605/594-6151</cntvoice>
<cnttdd>605/594-6933</cnttdd>
<cntfax>605/594-6589</cntfax>
<cntemail>custserv@usgs.gov</cntemail>
<hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M - F (-6h CST/-5h CDT GMT)</hours>
<cntinst>The USGS point of contact is for questions relating to the data display and download from this web site. For questions regarding data content and quality, refer to: http://www.mrlc.gov/mrlc2k.asp or email: mrlc@usgs.gov</cntinst>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
<datacred>U.S. Geological Survey, National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA),</datacred>
<secinfo>
<secsys>None</secsys>
<secclass>Unclassified</secclass>
<sechandl>N/A</sechandl>
</secinfo>
<native>Microsoft Windows 2000 Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 1; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.0.0.535</native>
</idinfo>
<dataqual>
<attracc>
<attraccr>The information on data quality for Hawaii has not yet been completed. This landcover map and all documents pertaining to it are considered "provisional" until a formal accuracy assessment can be conducted.</attraccr>
<qattracc>
<attraccv>not available</attraccv>
<attracce>This landcover was completed by the NOAA coastal services center, and the formal accuracy assessment has not yet been completed. The U.S. Geological Survey can make no guarantee as to the accuracy or completeness of this information, and it is provided with the understanding that it is not guaranteed to be correct or complete. Conclusions drawn from this information are the responsibility of the user.</attracce>
</qattracc>
</attracc>
<logic>The NLCD 2001 database for the Hawaiian mapping zone consists of three main data products including: (1) per pixel classified land-cover data (2) sub-pixel percent imperviousness and (3) sub-pixel percent tree canopy density. Additional information may be found at http://www.mrlc.gov/mrlc2k_nlcd.asp.</logic>
<complete>This NLCD product of the Hawaiian mapping zone Land Cover layer is the version dated 10-28-08.</complete>
<posacc>
<horizpa>
<horizpar>N/A</horizpar>
</horizpa>
<vertacc>
<vertaccr>N/A</vertaccr>
</vertacc>
</posacc>
<lineage>
<procstep>
<procdesc>This landcover was completed by NOAA coastal services center and is available for download in its original format here. http://www.csc.noaa.gov/ccap/pacific/ This landcover data was crosswalked from the expanded NOAA classes to NLCD standard classes. Following the development of the best classification through decision tree modeling, additional steps were required to complete the final land cover product. The four classes in urban and suburban areas were determined from the percent imperviousness mapping product (described in the next section). The threshold for the four classes is: (1) developed open space (imperviousness < 20%), (2) low-intensity developed (imperviousness from 20 - 49%), (3) medium intensity developed (imperviousness from 50 -79%), and (4) high-intensity developed (imperviousness > 79%). Other classes of forest and non-forest were combined with the urban classes to complete the land cover product. Finally visual inspection of the classification was made with areas/pixels that were wrongly classified delineated first as an "area of interest" (AOI), subsequently then limited manual editing was done to eliminate the classification error within the AOI. The completed single pixel product was then generalized to a 1 acre (approximately 5 ETM+ 30 m pixel patch) minimum mapping unit product using a "smart eliminate" algorithm. This aggregation program subsumes pixels from the single pixel level to a 5-pixel patch using a queens algorithm at doubling intervals. The algorithm consults a weighting matrix to guide merging of cover types by similarity, resulting in a product that preserves land cover logic as much as possible. Acquisition dates of Landsat ETM+ (TM) scenes used for land cover classification in Hawaiian zone are as follows: Path62 /Row 46 on 02/14/2000 = Scene ID 70620460214200000 Path62 /Row 46 on 12/30/2000 = Scene ID 70620461230200000 Path62 /Row 46 on 02/03/2002 = Scene ID 70620460203200200 Path62 /Row 47 on 02/14/2000 = Scene ID 70620470214200000 Path62 /Row 47 on 06/05/2000 = Scene ID 70620470605200000 Path62 /Row 47 on 01/31/2001 = Scene ID 70620470131200100 Path62 /Row 47 on 05/23/2001 = Scene ID 70620470523200100 Path62 /Row 47 on 01/02/2002 = Scene ID 70620470102200200 Path62 /Row 47 on 01/05/2003 = Scene ID 70620470105200300 Path62 /Row 47 on 02/22/2003 = Scene ID 70620470222200300 Path63 /Row 46 on 02/05/2000 = Scene ID 70630460205200000 Path63 /Row 46 on 09/16/2000 = Scene ID 70630460916200000 Path63 /Row 46 on 01/06/2001 = Scene ID 70630460106200100 Path63 /Row 46 on 01/22/2001 = Scene ID 70630460122200100 Path63 /Row 46 on 02/23/2001 = Scene ID 70630460223200100 Path63 /Row 46 on 08/02/2001 = Scene ID 70630460802200100 Path63 /Row 46 on 10/05/2001 = Scene ID 70630461005200100 Path63 /Row 46 on 01/09/2002 = Scene ID 70630460109200200 Path63 /Row 46 on 09/22/2002 = Scene ID 70630460922200200 Path63 /Row 46 on 01/28/2003 = Scene ID 70630460128200300 Path64 /Row 45 on 02/12/2000 = Scene ID 70640450212200000 Path64 /Row 45 on 02/28/2000 = Scene ID 70640450228200000 Path64 /Row 45 on 05/24/2002 = Scene ID 70640450524200200 Path64 /Row 45 on 07/27/2002 = Scene ID 70640450727200200 Path65 /Row 45 on 02/19/2000 = Scene ID 70650450219200000 Path65 /Row 45 on 12/19/2000 = Scene ID 70650451219200000 Path65 /Row 45 on 09/01/2001 = Scene ID 70650450901200100 Path65 /Row 45 on 12/22/2001 = Scene ID 70650451222200100 Path66 /Row 45 on 08/02/1999 = Scene ID 70660450802199900 Path66 /Row 45 on 01/09/2000 = Scene ID 70660450109200000 Path66 /Row 45 on 12/26/2000 = Scene ID 70660451226200000 Path66 /Row 45 on 01/11/2001 = Scene ID 70660450111200100 Landsat data and ancillary data used for the land cover prediction - Data Type of DEM composed of 1 band of Continuous Variable Type. Data Type of Slope composed of 1 band of Continuous Variable Type. Data Type of Aspect composed of 1 band of Categorical Variable Type. Data type of Position Index composed of 1 band of Continuous Variable Type.</procdesc>
<srcused>Landsat ETM, DOQQ, USDA, FIA, DEM, National Center,EROS, IKONOS</srcused>
<procdate>Unknown</procdate>
<srcprod>USGS NLCD</srcprod>
<proccont>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Customer Services Representative</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>USGS/EROS</address>
<address>47914 252nd Street</address>
<city>Sioux Falls</city>
<state>SD</state>
<postal>57198-0001</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>605/594-6151</cntvoice>
<cnttdd>605/594-6933</cnttdd>
<cntfax>605/594-6589</cntfax>
<cntemail>custserv@usgs.gov</cntemail>
<hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M - F (-6h CST/-5h CDT GMT)</hours>
</cntinfo>
</proccont>
</procstep>
</lineage>
</dataqual>
<spdoinfo>
<direct>Raster</direct>
<rastinfo>
<rasttype>Pixel</rasttype>
<rowcount>12618</rowcount>
<colcount>19439</colcount>
<vrtcount>1</vrtcount>
</rastinfo>
</spdoinfo>
<spref>
<horizsys>
<planar>
<mapproj>
<mapprojn>Albers Conical Equal Area</mapprojn>
<albers>
<stdparll>8.000000</stdparll>
<stdparll>18.000000</stdparll>
<longcm>-157.000000</longcm>
<latprjo>3.000000</latprjo>
<feast>0.000000</feast>
<fnorth>0.000000</fnorth>
</albers>
</mapproj>
<planci>
<plance>row and column</plance>
<coordrep>
<absres>30.000000</absres>
<ordres>30.000000</ordres>
</coordrep>
<plandu>meters</plandu>
</planci>
</planar>
<geodetic>
<horizdn>WGS 84</horizdn>
<ellips>WGS 84</ellips>
<semiaxis>6378137.000000</semiaxis>
<denflat>298.257222</denflat>
</geodetic>
</horizsys>
</spref>
<eainfo>
<detailed>
<enttyp>
<enttypl> Layer_1</enttypl>
<enttypd>NLCD Land Cover Layer</enttypd>
<enttypds>National Land Cover Database 2001</enttypds>
</enttyp>
<attr>
<attrlabl>ObjectID</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Internal feature number</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Count</attrlabl>
<attrdef>A nominal integer value that designates the number of pixels that have each value in the file; histogram column in ERDAS Imagine raster attributes table</attrdef>
<attrdefs>NLCD 2001</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Integer</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Value</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Land Cover Class Code Value. Class definitions marked with an asterisk (*) are Coastal NLCD Classes only.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>NLCD 2001</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>1</edomv>
<edomvd>No data value, Alaska zones only</edomvd>
<edomvds>NLCD 2001 land cover class descriptions</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>11</edomv>
<edomvd>Open Water - All areas of open water, generally with less than 25% cover or vegetation or soil</edomvd>
<edomvds>NLCD 2001 land cover class descriptions</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>12</edomv>
<edomvd>Perennial Ice/Snow - All areas characterized by a perennial cover of ice and/or snow, generally greater than 25% of total cover.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NLCD 2001 land cover class descriptions</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>21</edomv>
<edomvd>Developed, Open Space - Includes areas with a mixture of some constructed materials, but mostly vegetation in the form of lawn grasses. Impervious surfaces account for less than 20 percent of total cover. These areas most commonly include large-lot single-family housing units, parks, golf courses, and vegetation planted in developed settings for recreation, erosion control, or aesthetic purposes</edomvd>
<edomvds>NLCD 2001 land cover class descriptions</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>22</edomv>
<edomvd>Developed, Low Intensity -Includes areas with a mixture of constructed materials and vegetation. Impervious surfaces account for 20-49 percent of total cover. These areas most commonly include single-family housing units.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NLCD 2001 land cover class descriptions</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>23</edomv>
<edomvd>Developed, Medium Intensity - Includes areas with a mixture of constructed materials and vegetation. Impervious surfaces account for 50-79 percent of the total cover. These areas most commonly include single-family housing units.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NLCD 2001 land cover class descriptions</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>24</edomv>
<edomvd>Developed, High Intensity - Includes highly developed areas where people reside or work in high numbers. Examples include apartment complexes, row houses and commercial/industrial. Impervious surfaces account for 80 to100 percent of the total cover.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NLCD 2001 land cover class descriptions</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>31</edomv>
<edomvd>Barren Land (Rock/Sand/Clay) - Barren areas of bedrock, desert pavement, scarps, talus, slides, volcanic material, glacial debris, sand dunes, strip mines, gravel pits and other accumulations of earthen material. Generally, vegetation accounts for less than 15% of total cover.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NLCD 2001 land cover class descriptions</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>32</edomv>
<edomvd>Unconsolidated Shore* - Unconsolidated material such as silt, sand, or gravel that is subject to inundation and redistribution due to the action of water. Characterized by substrates lacking vegetation except for pioneering plants that become established during brief periods when growing conditions are favorable. Erosion and deposition by waves and currents produce a number of landforms representing this class.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NLCD 2001 land cover class descriptions</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>41</edomv>
<edomvd>Deciduous Forest - Areas dominated by trees generally greater than 5 meters tall, and greater than 20% of total vegetation cover. More than 75 percent of the tree species shed foliage simultaneously in response to seasonal change.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NLCD 2001 land cover class descriptions</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>42</edomv>
<edomvd>Evergreen Forest - Areas dominated by trees generally greater than 5 meters tall, and greater than 20% of total vegetation cover. More than 75 percent of the tree species maintain their leaves all year. Canopy is never without green foliage.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NLCD 2001 land cover class descriptions</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>43</edomv>
<edomvd>Mixed Forest - Areas dominated by trees generally greater than 5 meters tall, and greater than 20% of total vegetation cover. Neither deciduous nor evergreen species are greater than 75 percent of total tree cover.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NLCD 2001 land cover class descriptions</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>51</edomv>
<edomvd>Dwarf Scrub - Alaska only areas dominated by shrubs less than 20 centimeters tall with shrub canopy typically greater than 20% of total vegetation. This type is often co-associated with grasses, sedges, herbs, and non-vascular vegetation.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NLCD 2001 land cover class descriptions</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>52</edomv>
<edomvd>Shrub/Scrub - Areas dominated by shrubs; less than 5 meters tall with shrub canopy typically greater than 20% of total vegetation. This class includes true shrubs, young trees in an early successional stage or trees stunted from environmental conditions.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NLCD 2001 land cover class descriptions</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>71</edomv>
<edomvd>Grassland/Herbaceous - Areas dominated by grammanoid or herbaceous vegetation, generally greater than 80% of total vegetation. These areas are not subject to intensive management such as tilling, but can be utilized for grazing.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NLCD 2001 land cover class descriptions</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>72</edomv>
<edomvd>Sedge/Herbaceous - Alaska only areas dominated by sedges and forbs, generally greater than 80% of total vegetation. This type can occur with significant other grasses or other grass like plants, and includes sedge tundra, and sedge tussock tundra.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NLCD 2001 land cover class descriptions</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>73</edomv>
<edomvd>Lichens - Alaska only areas dominated by fruticose or foliose lichens generally greater than 80% of total vegetation.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NLCD 2001 land cover class descriptions</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>74</edomv>
<edomvd>Moss- Alaska only areas dominated by mosses, generally greater than 80% of total vegetation.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NLCD 2001 land cover class descriptions</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>81</edomv>
<edomvd>Pasture/Hay - Areas of grasses, legumes, or grass-legume mixtures planted for livestock grazing or the production of seed or hay crops, typically on a perennial cycle. Pasture/hay vegetation accounts for greater than 20 percent of total vegetation.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NLCD 2001 land cover class descriptions</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>82</edomv>
<edomvd>Cultivated Crops - Areas used for the production of annual crops, such as corn, soybeans, vegetables, tobacco, and cotton, and also perennial woody crops such as orchards and vineyards. Crop vegetation accounts for greater than 20 percent of total vegetation. This class also includes all land being actively tilled.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NLCD 2001 land cover class descriptions</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>90</edomv>
<edomvd>Woody Wetlands - Areas where forest or shrub land vegetation accounts for greater than 20 percent of vegetative cover and the soil or substrate is periodically saturated with or covered with water.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NLCD 2001 land cover class descriptions</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>91</edomv>
<edomvd>Palustrine Forested Wetland* -Includes all tidal and non-tidal wetlands dominated by woody vegetation greater than or equal to 5 meters in height and all such wetlands that occur in tidal areas in which salinity due to ocean-derived salts is below 0.5 percent. Total vegetation coverage is greater than 20 percent.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NLCD 2001 land cover class descriptions</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>92</edomv>
<edomvd>Palustrine Scrub/Shrub Wetland* - Includes all tidal and non-tidal wetlands dominated by woody vegetation less than 5 meters in height, and all such wetlands that occur in tidal areas in which salinity due to ocean-derived salts is below 0.5 percent. Total vegetation coverage is greater than 20 percent. The species present could be true shrubs, young trees and shrubs or trees that are small or stunted due to environmental conditions.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NLCD 2001 land cover class descriptions</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>93</edomv>
<edomvd>Estuarine Forested Wetland* - Includes all tidal wetlands dominated by woody vegetation greater than or equal to 5 meters in height, and all such wetlands that occur in tidal areas in which salinity due to ocean-derived salts is equal to or greater than 0.5 percent. Total vegetation coverage is greater than 20 percent.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NLCD 2001 land cover class descriptions</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>94</edomv>
<edomvd>Estuarine Scrub/Shrub Wetland* - Includes all tidal wetlands dominated by woody vegetation less than 5 meters in height, and all such wetlands that occur in tidal areas in which salinity due to ocean-derived salts is equal to or greater than 0.5 percent. Total vegetation coverage is greater than 20 percent.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NLCD 2001 land cover class descriptions</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>95</edomv>
<edomvd>Emergent Herbaceous Wetlands - Areas where perennial herbaceous vegetation accounts for greater than 80 percent of vegetative cover and the soil or substrate is periodically saturated with or covered with water.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NLCD 2001 land cover class descriptions</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>96</edomv>
<edomvd>Palustrine Emergent Wetland (Persistent)* - Includes all tidal and non-tidal wetlands dominated by persistent emergent vascular plants, emergent mosses or lichens, and all such wetlands that occur in tidal areas in which salinity due to ocean-derived salts is below 0.5 percent. Plants generally remain standing until the next growing season.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NLCD 2001 land cover class descriptions</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>97</edomv>
<edomvd>Estuarine Emergent Wetland* - Includes all tidal wetlands dominated by erect, rooted, herbaceous hydrophytes (excluding mosses and lichens) and all such wetlands that occur in tidal areas in which salinity due to ocean-derived salts is equal to or greater than 0.5 percent and that are present for most of the growing season in most years. Perennial plants usually dominate these wetlands.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NLCD 2001 land cover class descriptions</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>98</edomv>
<edomvd>Palustrine Aquatic Bed* - The Palustrine Aquatic Bed class includes tidal and nontidal wetlands and deepwater habitats in which salinity due to ocean-derived salts is below 0.5 percent and which are dominated by plants that grow and form a continuous cover principally on or at the surface of the water. These include algal mats, detached floating mats, and rooted vascular plant assemblages.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NLCD 2001 land cover class descriptions</edomvds>
</edom>
<edom>
<edomv>99</edomv>
<edomvd>Estuarine Aquatic Bed* - Includes tidal wetlands and deepwater habitats in which salinity due to ocean-derived salts is equal to or greater than 0.5 percent and which are dominated by plants that grow and form a continuous cover principally on or at the surface of the water. These include algal mats, kelp beds, and rooted vascular plant assemblages.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NLCD 2001 land cover class descriptions</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Red</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Red color code for RGB slice by value for canopy image display purposes. The value is arbitrarily assigned by the display software package, unless defined by user.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>NLCD 2001</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>100</rdommax>
<attrunit>CSS Color Value Percentage</attrunit>
<attrmres>0.1</attrmres>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Green</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Green color code for RGB slice by value for canopy image display purposes. The value is arbitrarily assigned by the display software package, unless defined by user.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>NLCD 2001</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>100</rdommax>
<attrunit>CSS Color Value Percentage</attrunit>
<attrmres>0.1</attrmres>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Blue</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Blue color code for RGB slice by value for canopy image display purposes. The value is arbitrarily assigned by the display software package, unless defined by user.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>NLCD 2001</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>100</rdommax>
<attrunit>CSS Color Value Percentage</attrunit>
<attrmres>0.1</attrmres>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Land cover class</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Land cover class</attrdef>
<attrdefs>NLCD 2001</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Text</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Opacity</attrlabl>
<attrdef>A measure of how opaque, or solid, a color is displayed in a layer.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>NLCD 2001</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>100</rdommax>
<attrunit>Percentage</attrunit>
<attrmres>0.1</attrmres>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
</detailed>
<overview>
<eaover>Attributes defined by USGS and ESRI. Class Red Green Blue 0 0.000000000 0.000000000 0.000000000 1 0.000000000 1.000000000 0.000000000 11 0.325490196 0.462745098 0.662745098 12 0.854901961 0.913725490 1.000000000 21 0.913725490 0.819607843 0.815686275 22 0.890196078 0.615686275 0.545098039 23 0.976470588 0.000000000 0.000000000 24 0.705882353 0.000000000 0.000000000 31 0.741176471 0.725490196 0.670588235 32 1.000000000 1.000000000 1.000000000 41 0.443137255 0.701960784 0.419607843 42 0.137254902 0.423529412 0.231372549 43 0.752941176 0.827450980 0.607843137 51 0.694117647 0.588235294 0.235294118 52 0.835294118 0.764705882 0.533333333 71 0.925490196 0.925490196 0.796078431 72 0.823529412 0.823529412 0.505882353 73 0.635294118 0.796078431 0.321568627 74 0.513725490 0.725490196 0.619607843 81 0.901960784 0.882352941 0.282352941 82 0.709803922 0.486274510 0.200000000 90 0.760784314 0.878431373 0.949019608 95 0.486274510 0.674509804 0.772549020</eaover>
<eadetcit>Attribute accuracy is described, where present, with each attribute defined in the Entity and Attribute Section. Note: To ensure all areas of the Hawaiian mapping zoneare completely covered, a 3,000 meter (100 Landsat pixels) buffer was added to the boundary of the Hawaiian mapping zone.</eadetcit>
</overview>
</eainfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Customer Service Representative</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>USGS/EROS</address>
<address>47914 252nd Street</address>
<city>Sioux Falls</city>
<state>SD</state>
<postal>57198-0001</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>605/594-6151</cntvoice>
<cnttdd>605/594-6933</cnttdd>
<cntfax>605/594-6589</cntfax>
<cntemail>custserv@usgs.gov</cntemail>
<hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M - F (-6h CST/-5h CDT GMT)</hours>
<cntinst>The USGS point of contact is for questions relating to the data display and download from this web site. Questions about the NLCD Hawaiian mapping zone can be directed to the NLCD 2001 land cover mapping team at the USGS/EROS, Sioux Falls, SD (605) 594-6151 or mrlc@usgs.gov.</cntinst>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>Downloadable data</resdesc>
<distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the USGS, no warranty expressed or implied is made by the USGS regarding the use of the data on any other system, nor does the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. Data may have been compiled from various outside sources. Spatial information may not meet National Map Accuracy Standards. This information may be updated without notification. The USGS shall not be liable for any activity involving these data, installation, fitness of the data for a particular purpose, its use, or analyses results.</distliab>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>Arc/Info Export Format and/or ArcView Shapefile</formname>
<formvern>ArcGIS 9.0</formvern>
<formspec>ASCII</formspec>
<transize>0.001</transize>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://seamless.usgs.gov</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
<accinstr>The URL http://seamless.usgs.gov provides a map interface that allows for data downloads within a customer defined area of interest. Zoom tools are available that can be used to investigate areas of interest on the map interface. The download tool allows the customer to capture layers from the map, utilizing the Seamless Data Distribution System process for downloading. A request summary page is then generated with the download layers listed. By clicking the "download" button on the summary page, a zipped file will be generated that can be saved on the customer's computer. The file can then be unzipped and imported into various user software applications.</accinstr>
<oncomp>Not available for dissemination</oncomp>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
<ordering>Contact Customer Services</ordering>
<turnarnd>Variable</turnarnd>
</stdorder>
<custom>Contact Customer Services Representative</custom>
<techpreq>ESRI ArcMap Suite and/or Arc/Info software, and supporting operating systems.</techpreq>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20081029</metd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Customer Services Representative</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>USGS/EROS</address>
<address>47914 252nd Street</address>
<city>Sioux Falls</city>
<state>SD</state>
<postal>57198-0001</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>605/594-6151</cntvoice>
<cnttdd>605/594-6933</cnttdd>
<cntfax>605/594-6589</cntfax>
<cntemail>custserv@usgs.gov</cntemail>
<hours>0800 - 1600 CT, M - F (-6h CST/-5h CDT GMT)</hours>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
<mettc>local time</mettc>
<metac>None</metac>
<metuc>None</metuc>
<metsi>
<metscs>None</metscs>
<metsc>None</metsc>
<metshd>None</metshd>
</metsi>
<metextns>
<onlink>http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html</onlink>
<metprof>ESRI Metadata Profile</metprof>
</metextns>
</metainfo>
</metadata>